Finding Aid for American Legion. Auxiliary. Erwin Prieskorn Unit #46 (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1921-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
American Legion. Auxiliary. Erwin Prieskorn Unit #46 (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1921-1992, 1970-1985
American Legion. Auxiliary. Erwin Prieskorn Unit #46 (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
3 oversize volumes
3 linear feet
9563 Be 2
Minutes of meetings, 1921-1992; Administrative files include annual reports, membership materials, committee records, correspondence, and subject files relating to fundraising events and charitable activities; and scrapbooks, 1932-1983, containing clippings about activities with a scattering of photographs and letters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was donated by the American Legion Post #46 Auxiliary from Ann Arbor, Michigan (donor no. 8230 ) in July 1994; additional materials came from Legion Post #46 (donor no. 10125 ) in 2008.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The American Legion Auxiliary of Erwin Prieskorn Unit #46, Ann Arbor, Michigan, held its first meeting on May 4, 1921 with an original membership of 33. At that time membership dues were $1.00 per year with $.25 of the dues being sent to the headquarters for relief work.
The auxiliary raised money in different ways: card parties, bake sales, rummage sales, book and card sales, and the sale of poppies. The money from poppy sales was used to honor America's war dead; the rest of the money was directed toward different community projects, including aid for servicemen and their families (especially during Christmas and Easter). Specifically, the auxiliary made donations to the children's home in Battle Creek, Michigan, the March of Dimes, the Salvation Army, the Michigan Heart Fund, and the Michigan Cancer Society. The auxiliary was also involved in hospital work, volunteering many hours to VA Hospitals in Ann Arbor and Battle Creek.
In 1992, with just one member willing to serve as an officer and only six members out of seventy actively involved, the organization ceased operation.
The records of the American Legion Auxiliary, Erwin Prieskorn Post #46, Ann Arbor, Michigan, date from 1921 to 1992. The record group is divided into three series: Minutes, Administrative, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Veterans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; American Legion. Auxiliary. Erwin Prieskorn Unit #46 (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
American Legion. Auxiliary. Erwin Prieskorn Unit #46 (Ann Arbor, Mich.); American Legion Building (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Parades.; Soldiers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Veterans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women.; World War, 1914-1918.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Minutes
  The Minutes series (1921-1992; 1 linear foot) includes meeting minutes for regular auxiliary meetings, as well as a scattering of minutes for the executive board and the joint executive board.
  - 1921-1992, 4 folders; 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Executive board and joint executive board meetings 1972-1986 (Box 1)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (1921-1992; 1 linear foot) includes information about memberships, finance, projects, correspondences and other various functions of the Auxiliary. Within the folder "Gold Star Mothers and Sons" are photographs of servicemen from Ann Arbor who died during World War I along with a photograph of each man's mother. Each set of mother and son photographs includes some brief biographical information.
  - Americanism Committee 1973-1985 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1979-1993, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary Communications 1932-1982 (Box 2)
  - Awards Received 1932-1982 (Box 2)
  - Boy-Girl/Youth Government Day 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - By-Laws 1969-1984 (Box 2)
  - Chaplain 1974-1978 (Box 2)
  - Child Welfare 1932-1933 (Box 2)
  - Committee Lists 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Convention Reports 1974-1987 (Box 2)
  - Endorsements for District Office 1959-1973 (Box 2)
  - Fall Conference 1975-1987 (Box 2)
  - General Correspondences 1950-1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Girls State 1975-1984 (Box 2)
  - Gold Star Mothers and Sons 1953-1958 (Box 2)
    (includes photographs of sons who died during World War I and their mothers)
  - History of Ladies Auxiliary 1992 (Box 2)
  - Junior Members Undated (Box 2)
  - Life Memberships 1963-1983 (Box 2)
  - Members Deceased 1978-1982 (Box 2)
  - Membership Applications (sample) 1928-1984 (Box 2)
  - Membership Dropped 1977-1982 (Box 2)
  - Membership Lists 1921-1986, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Memorial Day 1974-1982 (Box 2)
  - Monthly Meeting Notices 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Officers and Appointments 1977-1992 (Box 2)
  - Parades 1976-1980 (Box 2)
  - Past Commander's/Past President's Banquet 1973-1987 (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Viola Stoll Wilson, donor) (Box 2)
  - Poppy sales 1969-1988 (Box 2)
  - Presidents Office 1979-1982 (Box 2)
  - Publication of Erwin Prieskorn Post No. 46 ("Passing in Review") (Box 2)
  - Salvation Army 1976-1984 (Box 2)
  - Special Projects 1955-1982 (Box 2)
  - Standing rules 1984 (Box 2)
  - Veterans Projects 1975-1982 (Box 2)
  - Ways and Means Committee 1971-1979 (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks
  The series of Scrapbooks (1932-1983; 11 volumes) created by the Auxiliaries' various historians includes newspaper clippings photographs and letters.
  - 1932-1983 (scattered dates), 8 volumes (Box 3)
  - 1943-1947 (Volume 1)
  - 1950-1956 (Volume 2)
  - 1974-1975 (Volume 3)